בוקר
טוב. Boker tov. בוקר
מצוין. Boker metzuyan. בסיעתא דשמיא, B'siyata d'shmaya, with God's help. We are
starting a new and exciting מסכת. masechet. מסכת מכות. Masechet Makot. The
first discussion this morning is if it's מכות Makot or מכות, Makos,
but I'll go with מכות Makot and hopefully we'll work with that.
And may we, as we say, נעשה ונצליח, naaseh v'natzliach, let we
let us do and succeed. Okay, מסכת מכות Masechet Makot comes after
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
but really as we'll see in a minute, it's connected to a
previous chapter in סנהדרין Sanhedrin and not to the last chapter of
the אגדות. agadot. So it's not so much connected to פרק חלק,
Perek Chelek, it takes up exactly where we stopped the פרק perek
before about the נחנקים nechnakim
and continues the discussion from there. The discussion there was about עדים
זוממים. edim zomemim. I made this beautiful drawing on the board, we
will deal with that in a minute. That was our discussion before
and now we're going to pick up from it. There's three chapters,
as an overview, there's three chapters in מסכת מכות. Masechet Makot. The
first one deals with עדים זוממים edim zomemim and we'll discuss and
define those in length, and their penalties. The second one deals with
גלות, galut, like exiling people that have done something erroneously. And the
last one deals with מכות, makot, with lashes or beatings. You might
wonder, why not start with the third chapter if that's the only
one that deals with מכות? makot? But already in the first chapter
our עדים, edim, that is going to be the punishment that they
get, מכות. makot.
Okay, that's all I'm going to say at this point. All right.
What are עדים זוממים? edim zomemim?
The תורה Torah says if we have a situation, that poor guy
who's accused of doing something, right? Okay. How do we know he's
accused of doing something? There needs to be an עדות, edut, right?
There needs to be a testimony against him. On Monday at eight
o'clock in the morning, you whatever stole a hundred dollars from X.
Okay. You ראובן Reuven stole a hundred dollars from X. Okay. Now
if another set of witnesses, there need to be two witnesses, התראה,
hatra'ah, right? Warning. And they have to have been there and seen
it. If two other witnesses come and say, no no no, we
were there, we saw, he didn't take a hundred dollars, he took
two hundred dollars. Okay. Now we're talking about what happened and we
are what's called מכחישים makchishim one another, we are denying each other,
right? Or we're discussing the details of the situation. That's issue one.
But if there's two witnesses that tell on Monday morning at wherever
eight o'clock in the morning we saw you stealing eight- what was
it? a hundred dollars, just checking. And then two other witnesses come
and say no no no, maybe he stole the hundred dollars,
we're not arguing the case. What we are arguing is that you
on Monday morning at eight o'clock in the morning were not in
wherever this guy were. Okay. Wherever this guy was. This was in
תל אביב, Tel Aviv, you were in אילת. Eilat. We were together
snowboarding,
whatever in אילת, Eilat, or in the חרמון. Hermon.
Thank you. Second set of witnesses are not saying that the accused
was in another place.
They're saying that their witnesses- they're witnessing against the witnesses. So this
is like a very critical piece in order to understand these two
concepts that we're dealing with throughout this. One issue is הכחשה. hachashah.
הכחשה hachashah is there's two witnesses here,
we'll make them like this, and there's two witnesses here, right? And
they're arguing about the act. Was it a hundred dollars? Was it
two hundred dollars? Was it whatever? Okay. They're bringing different facts about
the deed.
This is this thing, the הכחשה hachashah addresses the deed, what happens,
okay? The הזמה hazamah addresses the witnesses. Somebody comes and says yeah,
he may be guilty,
he may
be whatever. ate pork, whatever, stole money, did whatever you want to
say he did. But you guys were not there to watch it.
You were with us and this is why I put the פסוק
pasuk here, sorry, עמנו הייתם. imanu hayitem. You were with us in
another place. Yes.
Yes, so עדים זוממים edim zomemim is such a big deal is
because since they were not even there, it's not a question of
they misperceived or whatever, it's they totally fabricated. Yes.
So, you know, kind of struggling to understand and, forgive me if
there's things that we missed, I find that it's like they completely
undermine this whole system. They use the system and the fact that
we believe people and the fact that we bring people to court
and all that in order to maybe settle a personal account they
had with this guy or whatever. But they misuse the system to
upheaval it. Okay, so this is like a critical difference that is
important to remember, okay? We are not talking about the deed. The
guy may be guilty as charged.
It's a different situation.
Wait, in a base case, it's a good question. Like let's say,
you know, the accused was with us. You say the deed was
on the חרמון Chermon snowboarding and, you know, stole money, stole a
hundred dollars, stole someone's snowboard, but it couldn't have been because he
was scuba diving with us in
אילת Eilat at the time.
Right. It's the same thing almost to say you were with us.
But who?
Who you were with us? This is what I said to David.
There's a lot of pronouns in this joint.
Two groups of עדים. edim. Group A says this guy stole, you
know, a snowboard in the חרמון. Chermon. Okay. Group B says that's
impossible because the accused was with us in אילת Eilat scuba diving.
So isn't the fact that you're now you're making this up? So
you are arguing on the deed and they're arguing on the עדים.
edim.
Not arguing on the deed.
Yes, they are. He didn't steal because he was with us.
No, they're not. In that case, no, they're not.
They can't do that. This is not their business. If they want
to say, "You didn't do it," then that's here. That's under the
הכחשה. hachachasha. We're dealing with the deed, we're not dealing with the
qualifications of the witnesses.
Yeah, but I'm saying you didn't see him and he wasn't there
where you're saying he was because because the accused was with us.
No pronouns. Who? The second group of עדים edim says you couldn't
have possibly seen him steal in the in ירושלים Yerushalayim because he
was with us in תל אביב. Tel Aviv.
He was with us.
Yeah, the accused was with us.
That's fine. That's in this realm. There's two realms.
But I'm saying you're doing both.
Meaning, all three of us were together in the חרמון. Chermon.
Well, no, or even if it's just the accused was with us.
If the accused was with us in the חרמון, Chermon, you couldn't
have seen him in תל אביב. Tel Aviv.
Okay.
But I don't think that's technically...
This is this is the situation. We have to understand that we
are in a very like tiny, pixelated issue, okay? We are not
dealing with everything that happens in the court. If you if they
say, "Hey, we saw you steal," and they say, "Oh, yeah, we
were in the same place and no, you didn't steal."
Let's call they they and they.
Okay, these are just groups of עדים. edim. These people, these are
just group of normal עדים. edim. You know, I was in the
market and I saw you. You put your hand, I saw this
guy. You put his hand in the money box. I saw him
take whatever, a hundred dollars. No, you were wrong, it was a
stack of a hundred dollars. You only saw the outside, inside there
was another five hundred. We really saw you stealing blah blah blah.
Okay. Those set of עדים edim come in front of the judge
and they argue this poor guy's case, okay? That's fine. If they
dismiss him, if they end up dismissing him because there's too many
conflicting witnesses, they might say, "Okay, the guy goes. We don't know
what to do with him." That is הכחשה. hachachasha. להכחיש lehachachish is
like they deny each other, okay? This is not this case.
No, I understand that. But I'm I'm putting in a different...
I think what Michael is saying is the effect is the same
as what we technically define as עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Right. But
I think the answer is this is a very formulaic... רגע רגע
רגע. rega rega rega.
The effect is not the same in the sense that if I
get this correctly. In the sense that if I say I saw
you at eight o'clock in the morning in the market in ירושלים
Yerushalayim taking a hundred dollars, and they say, "I saw you at
eight o'clock in the market in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, yes, indeed, you were
there, but you didn't take a hundred dollars, you took a dress."
Okay. That's הכחשה, hachachasha, we can argue this out until the cows
come home. This is not the situation we're in. The situation we're
in, and there's another piece of the situation that we have to
bring to the forefront.
The judgment was complete, okay? The court is final. The court heard
everything and the poor guy is getting whatever punishment he's getting, okay?
Let's give him a punishment. What would that be? I don't know
what. Punish. Okay.
He didn't get it, right?
No, he did not get it, but... But there's a booming voice,
yeah, he's sentenced. Okay.
Sentenced. By the way, it's beautiful because sentence is a משפט, Mishpat,
right? Also in Hebrew it's משפט Mishpat sentence and to be sentenced
it's also to be in a בבית משפט. Beit Mishpat. Okay, so
okay, he got his sentence,
didn't yet happen. Let's make gallows. Nothing happened, even though we don't
have gallows, but I can do all my drawings, okay. Not yet
punished. Okay, now.
Oh, by the way, are you saying either capital or property cases
when you're...
Yeah, it can be anything. It can be anything. It is not
about the case. If it was about the case, we would be
here. It is about if we qualify the witnesses.
It has nothing to do with him. He maybe stole a billion
dollars at eight o'clock in the morning in the market in Jerusalem,
but they could have not seen him. They could have not been
the witnesses.
Right, so the same question as what I said. If the accused...
but the accused could not have seen... the second set of witnesses
could not have seen the accused because the accused was with us.
Not they're saying that you, the witnesses, were with us, the accused...
Yes, they're saying עמנו הייתם. Imanu hayitem.
No, I know, but I'm saying but what happens if they said
he the accused...
Then they have to come here, they have to come into the
court and be like we were with him and then we're going
to deny the action of the guy, what you're saying is the
guy did not do it. He was with us, right?
That's what you're saying.
But no, I'm also saying you witnesses were with us, you couldn't
have seen it, but now if they say the accused was with
us so you couldn't have seen it, the effect is the same,
but it's not a
challenge to the first set of witnesses, but I think the answer
is we don't care.
Exactly.
Right now we... I don't even know if we don't care, but
right now in our little pixelated space, we're not there, okay?
So would you say הכחשה Hach-chasha if the... if the first group
of witnesses said he stole $100 in Jerusalem and the second one
says that's impossible because all three of you were with us, the
accused and both of you were with us in Eilat, but he
stole $100 there, would that be זוממין? Zomemin? Okay, I think... because
all of
you were in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
So possibly I would go with yes, I'm a little scared.
The key thing is to invalidate these witnesses.
They're being invalidated sort of.
And where it is in the process. Okay, those are the two
important things. Okay? Yes? Kind of you're okay?
Where is it in the process?
The process is this is over. The judgment is over. He's been
sentenced. Yes, we checked all these witnesses. We talked like... had we
talked with them that we were all in Eilat, that would have
been a good time to do it now, right? Okay. There's a...
there's a... כרוז, Karoz, whatever. Like everybody knows this guy is now
on trial for whatever, come and talk to us about this case.
This would be a great time to come and say he was
with us. Okay. This goes all under this, the case of הכחשה.
Hach-chasha. We will do whatever we can.
They would not be זוממין Zomemin in this... at that part of
the process?
Who's they? These guys?
Yeah, if during the process
rather than the...
before the sentence.
Before the sentence, no, because we can cancel them. If they come
before the sentence and they say I think you were with us,
was it Monday or Tuesday? I'm pretty sure it was Monday 8
o'clock in the morning. Yeah, that's... yes, we saw you.
Passage to India, great movie.
They're not yet
זוממין, Zomemin, they're just witnesses. Right. Until a second set of witnesses
come in and say maybe you stole, maybe you didn't steal, we
don't know anything about this, but you guys could not have been
there to see him.
But I'm asking that if this all occurs before the sentencing, then
they are not זוממין. Zomemin. No. Okay.
They are זוממין Zomemin only after the
sentence.
At this point, oops, that's
not going to
write.
Just invalidated witnesses going forward.
Yes, so not זוממין, Zomemin,
not killed if they want to kill.
Right. And these second set...
Oh we made a mistake, it wasn't Monday, it was Tuesday. Yes
there's other witnesses. Oh you're right. Right.
So these second set of witnesses have to come at a specific
time? Yes. Right here. After the sentence, before it's executed.
Right here. Between the sentence, so it's like the דין Din is
done. They had time to change their mind. זוממין Zomemin is a...
is like a difficult word. It implies there was an intent to
do something.
Not to get into more trouble than I am already, but if
you think of אשת חיל, Eshet Chayil, זממה שדה ותקחהו, Zamemah sadeh
vatikachehu, like she...
She thinks how to get this done. She sees a field, right,
and she plots how to acquire it, and then she acquires it.
She takes it. So זוממים Zomemim has this sense in the word
that there is a plot in their mind. They're trying to do
something that they should not be doing. The punishment to them is
going to
be—in
most cases—exactly.
That's what we're—that's the whole intro.
The punishment to them is going to be whatever you deem this
poor guy to be getting, that's what you now are going to
get. Okay? So he stole—you're telling everybody that he stole a million
dollars? No, that's too high. Let's go with a hundred because million
might have other issues to go with it. Let's say you say
that he stole a hundred dollars and he now has to pay
it back, you pay it back to whoever you say he stole
from.
Okay? ועשית לו כאשר זמם Va'asita lo ka'asher zamam and we'll see
it in a minute.
Wait, why would it be you pay it back to whoever he
stole from? You might not have stolen from that guy at all.
It should be paid back to this guy.
Now it's done. The sentence is done. So we decided the guy
is guilty. Yes indeed, he did that
crime, okay. We're going to give him whatever punishment we're going to
give him.
These guys show up and be like haha, you can't be witnesses
in this case, you were with us.
They will get the punishment that they wanted him to get.
Yeah, meaning if he would have lost a hundred dollars, then they
have to pay him a hundred dollars. Not that if David would
have gained a hundred dollars, they pay David a hundred dollars.
Depends where we are. I would want to say depends where we
are, but I don't—I don't know. Okay! Let's read the first משנה
Mishnah in מסכת מכות. Masechet Makkot. Very
good. Okay, thank you. You're welcome. Thank you. Okay. And we'll see—let
me please read the משנה Mishnah and then analyze it a little
bit more, and then we'll see that the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask some of the questions that we are going to ask
and is going to deal with it extensively, so bear with me.
כיצד העדים נעשים זוממים? Keitzad ha'edim na'asim zomemim? How do witnesses become
זוממים? zomemim? And as we'll see, this is the wrong question for
this
משנה. Mishnah. I'm already giving it to you so that you'll ask
me in a minute.
Huh? Memory of the גמרא. Gemara. I'm glad.
I don't—I had to learn it.
Ask the question! The question is really how the—'cause the question was
right now כיצד העדים נעשים זוממים, Keitzad ha'edim na'asim zomemim, how do
we have situations that the עדים, edim, where the witnesses become זוממים?
zomemim? And really the question should be, as we'll see in a
minute, how we have situations that the עדים edim are not זוממים.
zomemim. Now, I have an idea. I did not hear it anywhere,
so if I'm wrong, just like don't—don't shoot me right away. But
I think what the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara who's going
to reverse the question kind of a hundred and eighty degrees and
yet ask the same thing is like in what situations can we
punish them like we do to this guy and in what situations
can't we? And we're going to focus on the situations we can't.
There are going to be situations that we can't, you'll see in
a minute. I'll—I'll introduce it just so that you have an example
and you can visualize it. If he's guilty of stealing a hundred
dollars, they can pay a hundred dollars. But if he's guilty
of killing somebody by mistake, his punishment is going to have to
be—his, the accused—his punishment is going to have to be exile. That's
a punishment for a variety of reasons that they cannot get. They
will get a different punishment. Okay? So we are dealing in our
first דף daf in
the—hence מכות.
Makkot.
Hence מכות Makkot and that's why—that was the intro—that really most of
the מכות makkot are in the end but there's מכות makkot already
coming into this first דף daf of the ultimate punishment that these
guys are going to do in a case when they were זוממים,
zomemim, i.e., the judgment was declared, he's found guilty, and somebody comes
and disqualifies these זוממים. zomemim.
And in this four—רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says five—cases that they cannot,
just for a variety of פסוקים, pesukim, they cannot get the same
sentence, the same punishment that this guy is due to get. All
right. Hopefully this all will be helpful and not a waste of
time. Let's cover some ground.
Okay.
כיצד העדים נעשים זוממים, Keitzad ha'edim na'asim zomemim, two examples the
משנה Mishnah gives us. מעידים אנו באיש פלוני שהוא בן גרושה או
בן חלוצה.
Me'idim anu be'ish ploni shehu
ben grushah o ben chalutzah. In what cases would that make a
difference? רש"י Rashi says in the fourth line from the top, והם
כוהנים. vehem kohanim. If a guy is a son of a divorced
woman
and he's ישראל, Yisrael, who cares? Doesn't affect his status, doesn't make
any difference whatsoever. If he's a child of a כהן, kohen, we
will draw him in just a minute. If he's a child of
a כהן, kohen, he's going to lose his status. It makes a
difference. If they say, "Haha, we know your mom!
You...
let me take these away from
you guys
for a bit."
"Huh?" "We get it." "You get it? Maybe.
Father is כהן. kohen.
The mother is divorced.
They cannot marry.
Okay, if they have a child, he's a כהן kohen by status
but he can't function as a כהן. kohen. Okay, if they witness
against him, against his status, testify, sorry, if they testify against his
status, and this גמרא Gemara Aramaic English all at once.
They can't necessarily get the same status. That's a question. And they
can't necessarily get the same punishment just because they're in a different
category. Okay, that's situation one.
And they're going to get forty lashes. We will talk, God willing,
about lashes and forty. Hold the thought. Second situation: מעידים אנו באיש
פלוני שהוא חייב לגלות. אין אומרים יגלה זה תחתיו אלא לוקה ארבעים.
Me'idim anu be'ish ploni she'hu chayav liglot. Ein
omrim yigleh zeh tachtav ela lokeh arba'im.
They testify against somebody who deserves to be exiled. What is the
situation of somebody who deserves to be exiled? This is somebody who
killed another person בשגגה, bishgaga, by mistake. If this person is now
found guilty of killing another by mistake, he would get, he the
this poor guy, would get exile, but the witnesses cannot get the
same punishment for variety of reasons.
Deep breath, move on to the גמרא. Gemara. Yes, questions on the
משנה? Mishnah?
No? Good, okay.
All right. The גמרא Gemara immediately sees that our question is off.
Our question should not be כיצד העדים נעשים זוממים, Keitzad ha'edim na'asim
zomemim, how do the witnesses become עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, what do
you call them? Conspiring witnesses? But כיצד אין העדים נעשים זוממים מיבעי
ליה. Keitzad ein ha'edim na'asim zomemim miba'ei lei.
It should have said, "How do these witnesses are out of this
status?" Right? Because they're going to get a different punishment.
I disagree and I did not hear this so I'm a little
scared to go out on a limb, but I think their status
remains as עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. They just don't get the same
punishment as the guy. Okay, so maybe that's a way to understand
how the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara say opposite things but
still say the same.
Okay, ועוד מדקתני, ve'od midekatni, and furthermore, לקמן, lekaman, אבל אמרו להם
היאך
אתם מעידים שהרי באותו היום אתם הייתם עמנו במקום פלוני הרי אלו
זוממין.
aval amru lahem heich atem me'idim sheharei be'oto hayom atem
hayitem
imanu bemakom ploni harei elu
zomemin.
So this is exactly what we explained and is going to come
in page five of this מסכת. masechet.
That now the second set of witnesses, as we've beautifully drawn, attempt
to show that these are conspiring witnesses, right, that these are עדים
זוממים, edim zomemim, and they say עמנו הייתם, imanu hayitem, they cancel
them, and so they say באותו היום הייתם עמנו במקום פלוני. be'oto
hayom hayitem imanu bemakom ploni.
Why does it, why is it important that they say באותו היום
הייתם עמנו במקום פלוני, be'oto hayom hayitem imanu bemakom ploni, on that
day you were with us at that place? Because a testimony needs
to have two things.
Anyone?
We had it.
זמן, zman, בדיוק, bidiyuk, time and place. Okay, so if they just
say oh on that day, I don't know, I don't know how
it can go separate, but באותו היום הייתם עמנו במקום פלוני, be'oto
hayom hayitem imanu bemakom ploni, you were with us at a different
place, הרי אלו זוממין. harei elu zomemin. Okay, now תנא התם קאי,
tana hatam kai,
we are connecting ourselves now to the last relevant משנה. Mishnah. in
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Before פרק חלק, Perek Helek, before all the אגדות, aggadot,
the last thing we talked about was בת כהן, Bat Kohen, and
here comes the גמרא Gemara and explains to us: כל הזוממים מקדימים
לאותה מיתה חוץ מזוממי בת כהן ובועלה שאין מקדימים לאותה מיתה אלא
למיתה אחרת. Kol hazomemim makdimim le'ota mita chutz mizomemei bat kohen uvo'ala
she'ein makdimim le'ota mita ela lemita acheret.
Okay. The last thing we dealt with in סנהדרין Sanhedrin before we
went to פרק חלק Perek Helek with the אגדות aggadot was the
issue of בת כהן. Bat Kohen. If we have a בת כהן
Bat Kohen who has relations, right, has sex with somebody else, what
are the punishments? Anyone remembers? I would hate if you asked me.
But בת כהן כי תחל לזנות את אביה היא
מחללת באש תשרף.
Bat Kohen ki techel liznot et aviha
hi mechalelet ba'esh tisaref.
Okay, so it’s a מחלוקת machlokes Rabbi Shimon and Rabbi Yehuda.
תוספות, Tosafot, רש״י. Rashi. Right. Okay. So the בת כהן, Bat Kohen,
where is my napkin? Right.
So the בת כהן Bat Kohen her punishment is שרפה, srefa, right?
Fire. And בועלה, bo'ala, the guy who's with her, does not get
fire, gets חנק. chenek. Okay. Now we have a problem. You guys
are saying about the
בת כהן, Bat Kohen, you guys are saying about the בת כהן
Bat Kohen and her
paramour. We don't know this word, but okay, I will learn.
About the guy, that they had an illicit relations, some... okay, yes,
so far so good. What punishment should we give them?
Should we burn them or should we choke them? And why? Right?
Basically, that is the question. And because they get separate punishments, they
cannot get separate punishments. The שרפה srefa is unique to the בת
כהן. Bat Kohen. Other women that have illicit relations get also חנק
chenek and
not שרפה. srefa. This is something unique to her. Boom. The witnesses
cannot get the same
punishment. Further, what if they just saw her? What if they like,
what if
he's underage? Not saying anything. But those are all situations that come
up. Okay.
All right. ויש עדים זוממים אחרים שאין עושים בהם דין הזמה כל
עיקר אלא מלקות ארבעים. Veyeish edim zomemim acherim she'ein osim bahem din
hazama kol ikar ela malkot arba'im. So therefore we continue back to
the first משנה. mishna. There’s... let me see... there are... thank you,
bye... there are other conspiring witnesses that the court does not apply
those הלכות halachot that say that you need to get the punishment
of the people that you are doing a testimony instead. Rather they
get the lashes. Okay.
רגע. Rega. Continuing.
Okay.
Continue.
כיצד? Keitzad? כיצד, Keitzad, sorry, how, what is the situation, it's exactly
what we explained, the גמרא Gemara is just unpacking it.
מעידים אנו באיש פלוני, Me'idim anu be'ish ploni, who's
the
פלוני, ploni, okay, שהוא בן גרושה או בן חלוצה.
shehu ben gerusha
o ben chalutza. אין אומרים יעשה זה בן גרושה ובן חלוצה תחתיו
אלא לוקה את הארבעים. Ein omrim ya'aseh zeh ben gerusha uven chalutza
tachtav ela lokeh et ha'arba'im. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara just unpacked
what we say. We can't... if this guy, sorry, back to the
son of a כהן Kohen here on the stand, okay? They said
that he has a false status. His father is a כהן, Kohen,
so by his father he should be a כהן, Kohen, but he's
the son of a relationship that should not have happened.
Therefore he has... his last name might be כהן, Kohen, but he
cannot function as a כהן Kohen for all practical purposes. He lost
the status through this relationship. Now the גמרא Gemara adds, the משנה
mishna already adds another status, this is the חלוצה. chalutza. Who's the
חלוצה? chalutza?
חלוצה chalutza is the woman whose husband died and the brother of
the husband did not marry her to continue the lineage. Had she
just been a widow, she could have married the
כהן. Kohen. She's an אלמנה, almana, she's a widow. Had she just
been a widow, she'd been fine, if she was like, whatever, a
widow and no, her husband doesn't have any brothers, right? But if
the husband has brothers and she went through the חליצה chalitza through
the shoe throwing thing ceremony,
yes? If she's a
חלוצה, chalutza, she's...
Regardless, she cannot marry a כהן. kohen. Actually, we don't care so
much if she can marry, she cannot conceive from a כהן. kohen.
Once they have a child, his name might be כהן, kohen, but
he's a חלל. chalal.
חלל, chalal, very interesting word in Hebrew. It's in modern Hebrew it's
sometimes used for somebody who died.
Okay, like in a war, he's a חלל. chalal. Wow, how is
it all connected? He's מתחלל, mitchalel, he became an empty space for
this job. He can't function in this כהונה kehunah place.
And so an astronaut, is that חלל chalal also?
If it's going into space, it's like whatever, empty place. I don't
know how they travel the world. There's a lot of words that
are connected to this root. חליל chalil is a flute, like it's
an empty reed, right, with spaces. So there's there's something to do
with that spot. His status changes. He's not anymore a כהן kohen
that can function in the כהונה, kehunah, he's a חלל. chalal.
Does he eat
קדושה?
kedushah? There's there's discussion about that, like what can he do? Can
he go to a cemetery?
Does he not eat from the תרומה? terumah? Now we'll see in
a minute. It's a
problem, he can't use the no status.
His father remains a
כהן. kohen. You'll see it in a minute. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask all the questions we haven't quite formulated, we're just
like stunned by what's going on.
Okay, breathing, we're okay.
Okay. מנהני מילי? manei hani mili? Hey,
how do we know this? How do we know that if these
witnesses basically kill his status, right? They just came and said, "Ay,
whoa, yeah, your mom was in a forbidden relationship with a כהן,
kohen, therefore you're not a כהן." kohen. How do we know that
they are not going to get the same consequences
as the no-כהן kohen guy? אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי אמר ריש לקיש Amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi Amar
Resh Lakish דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, the Torah says, ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם,
va'asitem lo
ka'asher zamam, לו ולא לזרעו. lo v'lo l'zaro. Okay, it says about
the עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, do to them as they conspired to
do. I.e., let's take an extreme example. They come and they testify
against somebody who desecrated שבת. Shabbat. What do we do with somebody
who desecrated שבת? Shabbat? Kill him? How?
Stoning, right? Okay, so we should have stoned him. Oops, they're זוממים,
zomemim, they get the stoning. Okay. What is the problem with the
כהן kohen if we take away his status? How do we give
them that punishment?
The Torah in the case of the עדים זוממים edim zomemim says,
ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם, va'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, do to these bad
witnesses whatever they conspired to do to the accused.
If he's going to be stoned, he's going to go away free,
you guys are going to be stoned. But if he's not a
כהן, kohen, what are we going to do with them?
Even if they're כהנים, kohanim, we'll see in a minute. Even if
they're כהנים, kohanim, here's the problem I'm already giving you and then
you'll see the גמרא Gemara unpacking it.
Even if they are כהנים, kohanim, which they might be, I can
take away their status, but taking away his status also means his
future generations.
And the Torah says about the עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, ועשיתם לו,
va'asitem lo, לו lo with a vav, to them, כאשר זמם, ka'asher
zamam, do to him, to this witness, what he conspired. But if
I take his status away, that's going to affect the future generations.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, לו ולא לזרעו, lo v'lo l'zaro, do to
him and not to his offspring. Okay, וליפסלו לדידיה ולא ליפסלו לזרעיה.
v'lifsalu l'didi v'lo lifsalu l'zarei. Let's
let's do it to him and not to his offspring. Can't do
it. Because that is not the punishment. We are in a form
of punishment that can't be applied because if we do it right,
we have to we would have to take the whole thing. We
can't take half the thing basically. We can't take half the status
from him. So there's no way we can punish them. Okay.
בעינן כאשר זמם לעשות וליכא. ba'inan ka'asher zamam la'asot v'leika. We don't
have that situation here. We are supposed to do what they conspired
to do. Hold on a second, let me just find it. רגע
rega. *rega*. רגע *rega*. Oh ready, you want to solve everything? Well,
because we had in
the
משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*, we had two
cases where they're going to get lashes. רגע רגע *rega rega*, we'll
come to the lashes and even though not in the text, we'll
try to understand what
why lashes and what what is the meaning of it? Okay. Of
it. Okay, okay, okay.
Okay.
All right. Okay, בר פדא *Bar Pada*, right? בר פדא אומר *Bar
Pada omer*, he says: קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. I love, I have
to say this just because it's such a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* פסוק
passuk. *pasuk*, and then we'll try to unpack it. Okay. בר פדא
אומר קל וחומר ומה המחלל אינו מתחלל הבא לחלל ולא חילל אינו
דין שלא יתחלל *Bar Pada omer kal vachomer uma hamichalel eino mitchalel
haba lechalel velo chilel eino din shelo yitchalel*.
This is whatever, give it to kids to have fun with it.
Okay, let's unpack. ומה המחלל אינו מתחלל הבא לחלל ולא חילל אינו
דין שלא יתחלל *uma hamichalel eino mitchalel haba lechalel velo chilel eino
din shelo yitchalel*.
Okay.
This,
who's the מחלל *michalel* and who's מתחלל *mitchalel* and what is going
on here? Where is my other color that I
dropped somewhere?
Okay. All right. This כהן Kohen. *kohen*, right? He has a relationship
with let's say with a divorced woman.
Their son is going to be a חלל *chalal*.
Okay. They have a child, or maybe even she's they didn't get
married, she is not attached, and he has a relationship with her.
Now he's like, "Oh my god, I didn't know you were divorced,
blah blah blah, I want to continue being a כהן kohen, *kohen*.
Goodbye." Okay, they separate. She still has the kid. Okay, the kid
is a חלל *chalal*. He is what's called the מחלל *michalel*. He's
the one that caused this guy to be a חלל *chalal*. However,
what happens to his status? Nothing. Nothing. This is ומה המחלל אינו
מתחלל *uma hamichalel eino mitchalel*. He's causing somebody else but nothing happens
to his status. Okay? So this is somebody who's actively changing somebody
else's status
and yet nothing happens to him. הבא לחלל ולא חילל *haba lechalel
velo chilel*. So these guys that they just just conspired to change
his status but they didn't really, right? Because they were stopped by
these other guys. אינו דין שלא יתחלל *eino din shelo yitchalel*? Like
can we give them a worse punishment than we give him? This
guy did an act,
right? And nothing happens to him.
You know, I don't really see it as a parallel case like
that.
That's okay. I like I don't know what to do because this
is what how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sees it.
Yeah, but I mean I don't see how you can compare the
father who's sired a son, you know, if that's the word, and
these two people who are plotting against somebody else.
So the whole issue of עדים זוממים edim zomemim *eidim zomemim*
is there's many times in the conversation that you're like I don't
really get it but what's called גזירת הכתוב *gezeirat hakatuv*. This is
what the תורה Torah? *Torah* says. This is what our פסוקים *pesukim*
tell us. This is the best we can do with this situation
because we know that he is מחלל *michalel* and nothing happens to
him. They are because it's the פסוק passuk *pasuk* says זמם לעשות
*zamam la'asot*.
So
the תורה Torah *Torah* understands from it, we'll see in a minute,
the תורה Torah *Torah* understands from it that they conspired to do
but they didn't do for whatever reason. Okay, they were stopped.
You said something before about like this כהן *kohen* when he realized
that the woman was not of the proper status left her because
he didn't want to lose his כהונה *kehunah*?
Possibly. How would he lose his כהונה *kehunah*? He can't. He can't
because he's not allowed to marry a גרושה gerushah *gerusha*.
But if he marries her, does he lose I don't think he
loses.
He has to get out. He has to get out of this
relationship.
Right, but I don't think he loses his כהונה *kehunah*.
I don't think he can serve as a כהן *kohen* who's married
to a גרושה *gerusha*. Interesting. Okay. Like in modern ישראל *Israel* still
the רבנות *Rabbanut* will not let כהנים *kohanim* marry a גרושה *gerusha*.
And then once he separates then he can return?
He can return. Right. Okay. So he is a מחלל *michalel*. He
caused somebody else.
Right. These that only conspired, they didn't do anything. they didn't cause
him to be חלל. Can they possibly get the same thing? Okay.
רבינא Ravina has the same issue that you have. מתקיף לרבינא. matkif
l'Ravina. אם כן ביטלת תורת עדים זוממים. im ken bitalta torat edim
zomemim. If you go with this logic, we're not going to have
תורת זוממים, torat zomemim, right? The whole thing is going to go.
Let us go to page two.
Okay. רגע.
Okay. Continue. ומה הסוקל אינו נסקל. u'mah ha'sokel eino niskal. הבא לסקול
ולא סקל אינו דין שלא יסקל? ha'ba liskol v'lo sakal eino din
she'lo yissakel?
Kind of a parallel situation.
הסוקל, hasokel, okay, some more room. הסוקל hasokel is somebody who kills
another person with סקילה, skila, okay? You were on top of a
building, somebody walked underneath or you just like you got mad at
him, you threw a rock from the top, right? You killed another
person in סקילה. skila.
Yes?
Okay. He himself, the killer, does not get the punishment of סקילה.
skila. What does he get?
He gets סייף. sayif. He gets the punishment for somebody who killed
another person. So what the גמרא Gemara. is showing us is that
people that do things, they don't necessarily get the same punishment. It's
not all like tit for tat, you know, you did this, you're
going to get this.
הבא לסקול ולא סקל אינו דין שלא יסקל?
ha'ba liskol v'lo sakal
eino din she'lo yissakel? אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. ela mechvarta k'deshaninan me'ikara.
We have to go back to the beginning and say this: אשר
זמם לעשות לו. asher zamam la'asot lo. Only he can only have
what he...
the punishment is confined inside what he's זמם לו, zamam lo, exactly
to him. It can't be, the punishment can't move. We have only
so much room.
Okay.
אמר מר, amar mar, sorry.
Did I skip
something about once the verdict is carried out then you can't have
הזמה? hazama? You can't. Yes,
you
can't. This is what I said. We're right in this spot here.
Right. If it is, the verdict is carried out, we're done. We're
done. Even if this poor guy's dead. Right. We're not going back
and killing more people in order to avenge his death. If the
verdict is done, no.
But if
the trial is still going on, also, it's got to be this
spot here in the middle. The case is over, he was sentenced,
but it was not yet carried out. Right. So this is why
this line here.
Yes.
If these זוממין zomemin witnesses are proved to be זוממין zomemin after
the execution,
is there some punishment from heaven? Do they say?
They don't say.
I'm not reading God's mind.
But sometimes, sometimes in the גמרא Gemara they say,
I think there is an assumption that, you know, if they were
really זוממין zomemin and because of them, they're whatever, life will catch
up with them. But even living with the fact that you know
that somebody was executed on your account is also already a complicated
thing. So we don't add death to death in order to resolve
something that already was resolved.
But living with it, I mean that was their intention to live
with it. You know what I mean.
Possibly. Yeah, okay. I can't do anything. We're going to cover a
little bit. It's all complicated and we're going to cover a little
bit. Okay.
Next piece. ועדים אנו באיש פלוני שהוא חייב גלות וכו׳. v'edim anu
b'ish ploni she'hu chayav galut v'chulu. We're picking up back in the
משנה, Mishna. the next case. This was the case of the
בן גרושה ובן חלוצה. ben gerusha u'ven chaluza. The next case is
somebody
who is going to get גלות, galut, who's going to be exiled.
What is the case of somebody who's going to get exiled? מנהני
מילי? mina hanei mili? Where do we find these words? אמר ריש
לקיש דאמר קרא: amar Reish Lakish de'amar kra: הוא ינוס אל אחת
הערים. hu yanus el achat he'arim. הוא ולא זוממין. hu v'lo zomemim.
What is the case of somebody getting exiled?
We're done with this כהן. Can I erase that?
Oh, so good.
It's so good? Yeah, I need it. Okay, so I'm going to
take her away. Remember? Okay. She's the,
the בת כהן bat Kohen is important. Okay, fine, I'll put her
up here. The בת כהן bat Kohen is important for two reasons.
One because she teaches us that עדים זוממים eidim zomemim, cannot always
get the same punishment, and two because she shows up in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin and so she connects us to where we are in the
greater גמרא. Gemara Okay. And the משנה. So we'll put her here.
Now we're dealing with גלות. galut. Who gets גלות? galut? Somebody who
killed another person. The person בשגגה *bishgaga*
by mistake. Okay, and it's while we think about it as a
very ancient thing,
sadly, we can think about it in modern life like with driving,
right? A person drives, oops, I didn't mean it, somebody ran into
my car,
dead, right? That would be a situation of חס וחלילה *chas vechalila*
God forbid killing somebody בשגגה *bishgaga*. And even under that, there's,
sorry, there's two שגגות *shgagot*. There can be a שגגה במזיד *shgaga
bemeizid* and שגגה באונס *shgaga beones*. Like, okay, I'm driving near a
school, I'm going 25 miles an hour, I have my eyes on
everything, I'm, you know, I haven't been drinking, seatbelt, everything I'm doing
by law, somebody runs into my car. That would be אונס *ones*
like I was, I was forced to do something I didn't intend
to.
Or the flip side, I'm drinking, I don't care, I'm going 140
some miles an hour, can't even do that, kilometers, whatever, and oops,
I didn't see that there is a person walking by the side
of the road. Okay, that would be מזיד *meizid*. That would be
like I didn't mean it, but I did a lot of things
that—negligence—yes, serious negligence as opposed to really I didn't mean it. Okay,
the Torah's punishment, fascinating, is that this person who killed בשגגה *bishgaga*
goes to גלות galut. *galut*. He's being exiled, right, to the,
oh gosh, I forgot what it's called, the city, yes, the ערי
מקלט *arei miklat*. Sorry, I was like עיר נידחת *ir nidachat*? No,
עיר מקלט *ir miklat*. Thank you. Okay, he's going to an עיר
מקלט *ir miklat*. Now, it's a, it's in a way, very beautiful
concept, the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*. It is not a prison, right?
'Cause what happens when you send people to prison and they come
out better criminals than they started out, right? The עיר מקלט *ir
miklat* has teachers, has like, you know, whatever, a place to rehabilitate,
but he needs to be away from society to think, how did
he come to that situation? Okay, what does the פסוק passuk, *pasuk*
say? We are being referred to דברים Devarim, *Devarim*, right? הוא ינוס
אל אחת הערים *hu yanus el achat he'arim*. הוא ולא זוממים zomemim
*hu velo zomemim*. The Torah understands from this word הוא *hu* that
this guy who's now standing here in court for killing somebody בשגגה
*bishgaga*, he is going to be exiled. הוא ולא זוממים *hu velo
zomemim*. No one else can take the punishment away from him. So
the זוממים *zomemim*, it might be like going to a great place,
right? Going to the עיר מקלט *ir miklat*, going away from society.
Maybe it's a good thing. We're not giving them a punishment that,
we're not giving them that punishment. Okay. רבי יוחנן אומר קל וחומר
ומה הוא שעשה מעשה במזיד אינו גולה הן שלא עשו מעשה במזיד
אינו דין שלא יגלו *Rabbi Yochanan omer kal vachomer uma hu she'asah
ma'aseh bemeizid eino goleh hen shelo asu ma'aseh bemeizid eino din shelo
yiglu*. Okay, another, another situation where we come kind of, I want
to say to an impasse with this. Okay. If a person kills
somebody by mistake, he goes to עיר מקלט *ir miklat*, to גלות
*galut*. But what if somebody killed somebody on purpose? And for some
reason we don't have a full testimony around it. Maybe there was
no התראה *hatra'ah*, right? Maybe there was no warning. Maybe we don't
have enough witnesses. So the מזיד *meizid*, nothing happens to him. He
either we're going to kill him if we have a full שפיל
*shpiel* around him, or he's going to go away free. So the
מזיד *meizid* potentially gets nothing. The זוממים *zomemim* who didn't do anything,
right, they didn't kill anybody, they were just זוממים *zomemim*. Can we
really give them the same punishment and to give them גלות *galut*?
והיא נותנת והלא דינו הוא שעשה מעשה במזיד לא יגלי כי היכי
דלא תהוי ליה כפרה kaparah, הן שלא עשו מעשה במזיד נמי ליגלו
כי היכי דלהוי ליה כפרה kapara *vehi notenet vehalo dino hu she'asah
ma'aseh bemeizid lo yigli ki heichi dela tehei leh kaparah hen shelo
asu ma'aseh bemeizid nami liglu ki heichi delehei leh kaparah*. I'm trying
to cover a little bit of ground and maybe that backfires. אלא
מחורתא כדברי ריש לקיש *ela mechuverta kedivrei Reish Lakish*. We have to
go back. Like, we can't, we can't give them this punishment, the
גלות *galut*. We can't give them the punishment of the guy who
killed somebody במזיד *bemeizid*, right, because he either is going to die,
right, let's say he's going to get סייף *sayif*, or he's going
to go away free. Like, we don't have enough testimony. So he's
going to go away with nothing. Right? If somebody's accused of killing
somebody else, we can't give him a half punishment. Either we find
him guilty, we're going to kill him, or we don't find him
guilty, he's going free.
We can't give them that punishment because this פסוק passuk *pasuk* said
הוא ינוס *hu yanus*. He, the guy guilty, and no one else
will go instead of him. So we're in a bind. We can't
give any of these punishments, we can't give that punishment. Okay. this
option maybe there's some כפרה that can be done. Let's read a
little more. אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. Now
it's
like the גמרא Gemara has made so much progress and now it's
as if it's going back. אמר עולא רמז לעדים זוממין מן התורה
מנין. Amar Ulla remez l'edim zomemin min haTorah m'nayin. Wait. Where do
I have a hint for this whole business of עדים זוממין edim
zomemin in the תורה? Where from?
The גמרא Gemara says רמז לעדים זוממין והכתיב. Remez l'edim zomemin v'haktiv.
Like רמז, remez, you need a hint for עדים זוממין? edim zomemin?
It's a פסוק מפורש, passuk meforash, right? There is a
verse in the תורה that says clearly in דברים, Devarim ועשיתם לו
כאשר זמם. v'asitem lo ka'asher zamam. It says clearly. You should do
to him as he conspired. Why are you looking for a hint?
אלא רמז לעדים זוממין שלוקין מן התורה מנין. Ella remez l'edim zomemin
shelokin min haTorah m'nayin.
Like
no, no. I'm not really asking about the whole עדים זוממין edim
zomemin business. I'm asking about a hint that they can get lashes.
Where do I find a hint in the תורה that they can
get lashes? Okay. דכתיב. Dichtiv. I have a פסוק. passuk, That
פסוק passuk
is in דברים in פרשת כי תצא. Parshat Ki Teitzei. והצדיקו את
הצדיק והרשיעו את הרשע והיה אם בין הכות הרשע. v'hitzdiku et hatzadik
v'hirshiu et harasha v'haya im bin hakot harasha. Okay.
So this is the whole פסוק, passuk right? Says if there is
a fight between people and they come to the court and they
were sentenced and the court justified the righteous one and called like
the evil one guilty. And then the שופט, shofet, the judge, will
beat up the bad guy, the accused. Do you see the פסוק
passuk, on the side?
No, yes, maybe.
Okay. There is a פסוק, passuk. I promise you. It's in כי
תצא. Ki Teitzei. I think כה, kaf hey, if I see it
right, א' ב'. alef bet. Okay.
So now, huh?
25. 25-1.
Right, 25.
Okay. So now this is a strange פסוק pasuk? because
what is the קשר, kesher, what is the connection between the צדיק
tzadik who is justified and the רשע rasha who is accused? And
because the צדיק tzadik is justified, we beat up the bad guy?
Like על פניו, al panav, like on the surface, it looks like
it's a פסוק pasuk that doesn't make sense. Therefore,
in order to make sense out of this פסוק, we have to
say that we have a case here that the witnesses came and
they accused the good guy. They הרשיעו את הצדיק hirshiu et hatzadik
through a lie. And then different witnesses came and proved that the
first ones were זוממין. zomemin. Otherwise, the whole thing does not make
sense. And here is how the גמרא continues. אלא עדים שהרשיעו את
הצדיק ואתו עדים אחריני והצדיקו את הצדיק דמעיקרא. Ella edim shehirshiu et
hatzadik v'atu edim achrinei v'hitzdiku et hatzadik d'meikara. עדים זוממין Edim zomemin
accused the צדיק tzadik
and then
other witnesses said no, no, no, the צדיק tzadik is really righteous.
This is a time where
where am I? Okay. ושוינהו להני רשעים והיה אם בין הכות הרשע.
v'shavinhu l'hani reshaim v'haya im bin hakot harasha.
That's where we see that there are מכות makot to somebody
in a false trial, like somebody who was עדים זוממין edim zomemin
trial. Okay.
The גמרא is going to challenge this.
Can I ask a question? Yes. Yes. In that just recent discussion,
it seemed that the second set of witnesses, they're saying he, the
accused, was righteous. So which category does that fit into? Does that
fit into discussing the merits of the case?
It's not the כהן, it's not the גלות. Yeah.
But before you were saying there were two categories. One about discussing
the merits of the case and the other discussing about
It's all in the זוממין. zomemin. We're all here.
Yeah, but so but that
category implied that discussing We're
we're now in a detour. We're now in a detour. The question
in front of us is none of this. Okay. The question in
front of us is, okay, you're not giving them any of these
punishments, you're giving them lashes.
How did you
decide to give them lashes? Did you just make it up? No,
I found a פסוק.
Okay, I'm just saying
that the example given
sounds like it could be referring to the merits of the case
rather than how we defined זוממין zomemin originally as only when it
talks about they couldn't have been there. Here they're talking about whether
the accused is righteous or Exactly.
Exactly.
Yes, yes, and they'll challenge it right away.
This is just like whatever two
minutes to come to a further down stopping point. He says, why
are you going to this פסוק? Exactly what you're saying, why are
you going to this roundabout way? ותיפוק ליה מלא תענה, ve-tipok lei
mi-lo ta'aneh, משום דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה, mishum de-havi lav she-ein
bo ma'aseh, וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה, ve-chol lav she-ein bo ma'aseh,
אין לוקין עליו. ein lokim alav. So, you don't need to learn
the lashes from this roundabout way with the צדיק tzaddik and the
רשע, rasha, you can learn it from לא תענה, lo ta'aneh, לא
תענה ברעך עד שקר. lo ta'aneh be-rei'acha ed sheker.
If
there is a לאו lav that אין בו מעשה, ein bo ma'aseh,
if there is a 'don't do' that there was no action following
it, okay, as opposed to don't eat pork. Okay, so in order
to do that לאו lav you have to do something, right? You
have to have an action. But here there's a לאו שאין בו
מעשה. lav she-ein bo ma'aseh. There's lashes there. Let me just cover
a little bit more, and whoever is tomorrow is going to be
slightly unhappy with our progress. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. ארבעה דברים
נאמרו בעדים זוממים. arba'ah devarim ne'emru be-edim zomemim.
Four things are discussed with the issue of עדים זוממים, eidim zomemim
okay? אין נעשים
בן גרושה ובן חלוצה, ein
na'asim ben gerushah u-ven chalutzah,
and עדים eidim cannot become a son of a גרושה and a
divorcee, right, or a son of a חלוצה, chalutzah, they cannot take
on that status. ואין גולין לערי מקלט, ve-ein golin le-arei miklat, they
cannot be exiled. Three, two more. ואין משלמים את הכופר, ve-ein meshalmim
et ha-kofer, they don't
pay what do you call כופר? kofer?
Penalties? No, not penalty, atonement.
Like a ransom,
says
Sefaria. Okay. You don't pay כופר. kofer. ואין נמכרים בעבד עברי. ve-ein
nimkarim be-eved Ivri.
If this guy had to be sold as
עבד עברי, eved Ivri, the עדים זוממים eidim zomemim, are not going
to be sold instead of him, even if they caused that situation,
okay?
משום רבי עקיבא, mishum Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva added a fifth one,
אמרו, amru, אף אין משלמים על פי עצמם.
af ein meshalmim
al pi atzmam. Okay, they also they cannot redeem themselves by going
to another court and saying, oh actually we were עדים זוממים, eidim
zomemim let us pay you money and be off the hook.
Can't
do that. Okay, let's unpack. אין נעשים בן גרושה ובן חלוצה כדאמרן,
ein na'asim ben gerushah u-ven chalutzah ke-d'amran, we explained it already. ואין
גולין לערי מקלט כדאמרן, ve-ein golin le-arei miklat ke-d'amran, we explained it
already. ואין משלמים את הכופר, ve-ein meshalmim et ha-kofer, and we don't
pay this ransom or atonement money, right? כי סברי כופרא כפרה, ki
savrei kofra kaparah, והני לאו בני כפרה נינהו. ve-hanei lav bnei kaparah
ninhu. Okay, the כופר, kofer, paying this ransom is in order to
atone for an act. You זוממים didn't do an act. You conspired
to do an act but you didn't do an act. Therefore, you
cannot pay in order to atone something that you didn't do. Okay.
מאן תנא כופרא כפרה? man tanna kofra kaparah? Now we have a
little bit of a discussion that we'll try to unpack this כופרא
כפרה, kofra kaparah, that כופר kofer that is a כפרה, that is
atonement. Let's say we have an example, if we have an ox
that gored somebody, right? שור המועד shor hamu'ad needs to be killed
or pay for a fine. They don't get to pay. It's not
their thing, they don't get to pay.
Okay, okay, okay. Did I skip? No. Okay.
מאן תנא
כופרא כפרה? man tanna kofra kaparah? Let's unpack the conversation about the
כופר, kofer, about the ransom atonement money. אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav
Chisda, רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא היא דתניא, Rabbi
Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka hi detanya, we have a
teaching, ונתן פדיון נפשו, ve-natan pidyon nafsho, right? That's our פסוק
from שמות, Shemot, from משפטים. Mishpatim. If we are saying that they
need to pay, what are they paying?
How
much? What money? Are they paying the money of the ניזוק nizak
or are they paying whatever their fine
is?
Okay.
דמי ניזוק. dmei nizak. So one option is
they're paying what the person that was damaged, right? That is one
opinion that says דמי ניזוק. dmei nizak. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan, oh we read this already.
Sorry. אומר דמי מזיק. omer dmei mazik. So now we have two
different concepts. We'll leave the poor board. One is דמי ניזוק
dmei nizak and one is דמי מזיק. dmei mazik. מזיק. mazik.
Okay,
we
gave the example of the ox. The,
I'm just wondering if we were supposed to stop with our time.
Nobody's here.
I know.
Keep going. Sorry, did they not have room? Oh, you got booth?
Yeah. Well, I have shoes now.
Oh right, so why don't, okay, so let's
see if we can,
I'm going to cut that out
for a
second. Let's,
let's pause because this like goes into an extensive discussion about the
כופר kofer and the כפרה and how is that another aspect of
the עדים זוממים eidim zomemim that cannot be made on the עדים
זוממים to get the same punishment. So that would be the third
case of how they get a different punishment and not the punishment
of the, of the accused. Okay, hopefully shorter דפים dapim ahead and
more catchup. Thank you for being with us this morning.